<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss 
version="2.0" xmlns:iffy="http://tech.interfluidity.com/xml/iffy/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>tech — interfluidity</title>
    <link>https://tech.interfluidity.com/index.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[Feed for blog 'tech — interfluidity', generated by unstatic]]></description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 13:46:34 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>https://github.com/swaldman/unstatic</generator>
    <docs>https://cyber.harvard.edu/rss/rss.html</docs>
    <atom:link
    type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="https://tech.interfluidity.com/2024/03/27/tar-or-tgz/index.rss"/>
    <iffy:curation>
      <iffy:single/>
    </iffy:curation>
    <iffy:completeness>Content</iffy:completeness>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2024 10:55:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://tech.interfluidity.com/2024/03/27/tar-or-tgz/index.html</guid>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[A thing I've done over the last while is automate a lot of my sysadmin, using systemd timers to hit scala-cli scripts. I've built for myself a little framework that is incredibly in need of documentation, but that lets me define scripts very flexibly and can provide great step-by-step information about what happens and anything that goes wrong in brightly colored HTML e-mails. I love it. Much of what I do is back things up to a cloud service using rclone. Last night I wrote a script just to...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://tech.interfluidity.com/2024/03/27/tar-or-tgz/index.html</link>
      <title>tar or tgz?</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>A thing I've done over the last while is automate a lot of my sysadmin, using <code>systemd</code> timers to hit <a href="https://scala-cli.virtuslab.org/">scala-cli</a> scripts.</p>
   <p>I've built for myself a <a href="https://github.com/swaldman/mchange-sysadmin-scala/tree/main?tab=readme-ov-file">little framework</a> that is incredibly in need of documentation, but that lets me define scripts very flexibly and can provide great step-by-step information about what happens and anything that goes wrong in brightly colored HTML e-mails. I love it.</p>
   <p>Much of what I do is back things up to a cloud service using <a href="https://rclone.org/">rclone</a>.</p>
   <p>Last night I wrote a <a href="https://github.com/swaldman/mchange-sysadmin-scripts/blob/main/taskbin/backup-directory-as-tar">script</a> just to back up some directory. I ran into what I consider an age-old dilemma.</p>
   <p>Sometime early in my geekish career, I picked up the nugget that its best to keep important backups as straight <code>tar</code> files rather than <code>tgz</code> (or <code>tbz</code> or whatever), because if some bit gets corrupted, most of a straight <code>tar</code> will remain recoverable, while the compressed archive will just be toast.</p>
   <p>Is that right? Is it a real concern? I don't think I've ever experienced a corrupted archive, <code>tar</code> or <code>tgz</code>, but of course backup is a form of insurance, the whole point is to be resilient to tail risks.</p>
   <p>Still, searching the interwebs, I don't see a lot of people recommending uncompressed archives. Space is more of a bottleneck to me than CPU or time, so if the resilience advantage isn't significant, I'd compress.</p>
   <p>What do you think?</p>
   <hr>
   <p><strong>Update:</strong> Feel free to comment <a href="https://zirk.us/@interfluidity/112168423434044308">here</a></p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <hr>
   <div>
    by Steve Randy Waldman on 2024-03-27 @ <a href="https://tech.interfluidity.com/2024/03/27/tar-or-tgz/index.html" class="pubtime">10:55 AM EDT</a>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
</article>
<div class="after-article">
</div><!-- after-article -->]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
